Guide to the Francis C. Steinbauer Reston development and planning collection, 1962-1990
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Francis C. Steinbauer Reston development and planning collection
1962-1990
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Francis C. Steinbauer
C0152
1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
The Francis Steinbauer Reston Development and Planning Collection contains materials pertaining to Reston history and development. The material covers Francis Steinbauer career with Reston and the state of Virginia. The collection includes photographs, sales information and manuals, master plans, reports, memoranda, and memorabilia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Francis Steinbauer in 2004.
Biographical Information
Francis Steinbauer was a key participant in the development of Reston through the first twenty years of its growth as a major new community in Northern Virginia. In 1964 he joined Palindrome Corporation (later Reston VA, Inc), headed by founder Robert E Simon as Design Engineer responsible for the creation and governmental approval of site and construction plans for residential and commercial building lots, and for Reston streets, parking areas, underground utilities, lakes, dams, public facilities and amenities such as swimming pools, tennis courts, and playgrounds. When Gulf Oil Corp. took over the development of Reston in 1967, it created Gulf Reston Inc. as the entity to accomplish that task. Gulf Reston undertook the full range of development activities including major re zoning, land development and building of housing for sale, apartments, office buildings and retail centers. It also owned, leased and managed most of the projects that it built.
To accomplish the breath of these activities, the company employed between 175 and 200 people. Mr. Steinbauer was retained by Gulf Reston as chief Design Engineer, and over the course of the next ten years was given successively broadened responsibilities in Gulf Reston management. Positions include: Director, Engineering and Design; Vice Operations; and ultimately Executive Vice President and General Manager.
Along with corporate management responsibilities, Mr. Steinbauer was a primary company spokesman to local and state government bodies such as Fairfax County Board of Supervisors, Virginia Department of Transportation and Washington Airports Authority. He was also a company representative to the growth and very active Reston community.
In 1978, Gulf Oil sold its interest in the remaining 3,700 acres of undeveloped land in Reston to Reston Land Corporation a subsidiary of Mobil Oil Corporation. Its business strategy was to focus more on strategic land planning, zoning and construction of land infrastructure and amenities rather than on building offices and residences as was necessary in the earlier Reston years. Actual building construction was left to builder/developers to whom prepared building sites were sold. Mr. Steinbauer was retained by Mobil as Executive Vice President and General Manager, and in 1981 he was promoted to President of Reston Land Corporation. In addition to overall management of company operations, Mr. Steinbauer focused on governmental relations and securing innovative public funding for badly needed transportation improvements, two of which were a major highway bridge over the limited access Dulles Access Highway to better connect north and south Reston, and most importantly parallel travel lanes and exit ramps along the Dulles Access Highway to provide Reston direct road linkage to the greater metropolitan area.
In 1983 Mr. Steinbauer was promoted to President of Mobil Land Development Corporation Eastern Division. Headquartered in Reston, he provided senior management to regional development companies in Virginia (Reston and Colonial village in Arlington), Georgia (Windward and Brickton in north Atlanta), and South Florida (Sailfish Point and River Bridge in Palm Beach).
Mr. Steinbauer resigned from Mobil Land Development Corporation in 1985, thereby ending his twenty-one year professional relationship with the development of Reston, in order to join in partnership with the Henry A Long Co. in the development of Westfields, an 1100 acre corporate Business Park immediately south of Dulles International Airport. As President of Westfield Development Company has oversaw the critical stages of land use zoning, engineering, and land development. He also managed the construction of the Westfield International Conference Center. In 1990, Mr. Steinbauer formed Advisory Group Limited to provide strategic real estate development consulting services to developers, investors, banks, and creditors in the greater Washington/Baltimore area. Services provided over the next ten years to these clients ranged from preliminary feasibility analysis and pro-forma economics to land planning, zoning, engineering and construction management.
Scope and Content
The Francis Steinbauer Reston Development and Planning Collection contains materials pertaining to Reston history and development. The material covers Francis Steinbauer career with Reston and the state of Virginia. The collection includes photographs, sales information and manuals, master plans, reports, memoranda, and memorabilia.
Series one is title subject files. The material in this series includes mostly paperwork, such as pamphlets, magazine, articles, reports and various documents. The series is dated from 1962 to 1990 and is contained in boxes 1-3.
Series two is titled photographs. The series small and contains photographs of a dedication cermonies and other cermonies that Francis Steinbauer was involved in. The series is dated from 1964 to 1978 and is contained in box 3.
Series three is titled oversize. The has three items in the series which include a t-shirt and framed photographs. The series is dated in the 1970s and is contained in box 4.
Arrangement
Organized into three series.
Series 1: Subject Files, 1962-1990 (Boxes 1-3)
Series 2: Photographs, 1964-1978 (Box 3)
Series 3: Oversize, 1970s (Box 4)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds many other collection on the history and development of Reston, Virginia.
Index Terms
Persons:
Steinbauer, Francis C.
Geographical Names:
Reston (Va.)
Subjects:
Planned communities--Virginia--Reston.
Contents List
- Series 1: Subject Files, 1962-1990
  The material in this series includes mostly paperwork, such as pamphlets, magazines, articles, reports and various documents,
  - A New Blend of Human and Natural Resources (Industrial Advertisement Booklet), 1970s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    2.11
  - America's Best Suburbs in Ladies Home Journal-August, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    1.26
  - An Update/Analysis of the Reston Employment Base (February), Commission Schedule and Broker Registration Procedures (July), Associations Headquartered in Reston, Virginia (July), 1978 and 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1.19
  - An Introduction to Zoning, Site Plan and Subdivision Law in Virginia: By Robert F. Flinn, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    2.07
  - Building Action, Voice of the Metropolitan Washington Building Industry: A Place Called Reston (November), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    1.23
  - Business Report-Fairfax County Economic Development Authority, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    2.02
  - Fairfax County, Virginia (Informational Book), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    2.17
  - Final Report-The Economic Impact of Reston on Fairfax County Government: By Booz, Allen and Hamilton, Incorporated, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    2.20
  - For Business on the Rise a Highrise in the Reston Conference Center Complex, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2.16
  - Gulf Reston Home Owners Manuel, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    1.30
  - Gulf Reston Strategic Plan (GRI), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    2.08
  - House Beautiful with Reston Articles-October, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    2.09
  - House Beautiful: Small House (p.94)-October, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    2.19
  - House and Garden: Design House (p.160)-October, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    2.18
  - If You Really Did Your Homework, You'd Want Your Kids to Go to School in Reston-Reston, Virginia, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    1.14
  - Industrial Land Sales Analysis (Land Sales Potentials in Reston), 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    1.34
  - Just Watching Your Children Grow Up in Reston Will Make You Feel Like a Kid Again-Reston, Virginia, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1.13
  - Lady's Home Journal-15 Best Suburbs, Do You Live in One?-August, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    1.12
  - Map of Reston Community, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 19)
    3.07
  - Modern Zoning for Reston, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    2.10
  - News From Reston: Unique Agreement Signed, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    4.5
  - Our Schools Are Just One of the Reasons We Got the Ladies Home Journal Stamp of Approval, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 22)
    1.15
  - Planning Memoranda on Reston-Report to Simon Enterprises: By Arthur D. Little, Incorporated-January, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Planned Residential Community (PRC) Review Process, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 24)
    1.20
  - Reston Business Center, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 25)
    3.06
  - Reston Center for Industry and Government (Aerial View of Reston), 1970s (Box 1, Folder 26)
    1.11
  - Reston Demographics and Growth-January, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    1.21
  - Reston Development Plan (Map)-April, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    1.10
  - Reston Facts and Figures (Pamphlet)-August, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    1.09
  - Reston Facts and Figures (Pamphlet)-May, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    2.01
  - Reston: Gulf Oil Real Estate Development Company (Goredco)-April, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    1.36
  - Reston Home Owners Association (RHOA) is an Active Word (Informational Mailing on the RHOA), 1980s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    1.03
  - Reston Industrial Center for Research and Government, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 3)
    2.03
  - Reston Land Corporation: Marketing Plan Summary-By Siddal, Matus and Caughter Incorporated-January, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    1.35
  - Reston Market Profile: Major Employers, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    2.15
  - Reston Market Profile: Population, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    2.14
  - Reston Market Profile: Schools, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    2.13
  - Reston Master Plan-Community Facilities Plan (Map)-June, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    1.22
  - Reston Master Plan Report-March, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    1.29
  - Reston Master Plan: Report and Maps-May, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    1.28
  - Reston Master Plan (Map)-February, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    1.25
  - Reston Not Only Has Some of the Best Taxes and Labor in Washington It Also Has Trees, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 12)
    1.16
  - Reston: Reston Turns 20 and There's More Reason Than Ever to Celebrate (Advertising Pamphlet), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    1.02
  - Reston: The First 20 years (Advertisement Pamphlet), 1980s (Box 2, Folder 14)
    1.24
  - Reston, Virginia: Its Social Impact on Fairfax County-Prepared by Houston Park, Incorporated, Original Research by Mrs. Nancy Larson-July, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    1.32
  - Springe Prices-Commercial/Industrial, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    3.03
  - Spring Prices-Comparable, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    3.05
  - Spring Prices-Introduction to Programs, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    3.01
  - Spring Prices-Residential Plans, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    3.02
  - Spring Prices-Town Center, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    3.04
  - Survey and Nature Center Plan for Reston, Virginia-Prepared by Nature Centers Division National Audubon Society, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    1.33
  - The Best Reasons for Moving Your Company to Reston Are Not All Business, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 22)
    1.18
  - The Case for Relocating the Fairfax County Government Headquarters to Reston: Co-Authored by Gladstone Associates Gulf Reston, Incorporated-January, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    1.27
  - The First Village Reston (Informational Packet), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    2.06
  - The Reston Industrial Landsales Newsletter-August, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    1.08
  - The Reston Times: Lifestyle Cameo of Fran Steinbauer, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    4.3
  - The Reston Times Clipping: 13th Year-June, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    4.4
  - The Reston Story, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    1.31
  - The Restonian-August, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    2.12
  - The Urban Country Executive Form, Code of Virginia (As Amendment in 1973) Title 15.1 Chapter 15, County of Fairfax, Virginia-February, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    1.01
  - We've Always Told People to Buy Your Homes in Reston. This Year We're Making Sure They Get the Picture (Reston's Advertising Program), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    1.17
- Series 2: Photographs, 1964-1978
  The series small and contains photographs of a dedication ceremonies and other ceremonies that Francis Steinbauer was involved in.
  - All-Weather Wood Foundation Laying Ceremony (The Warren Katz House), 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    2.04
  - All-Weather Wood Foundation Laying Ceremony (The Warren Katz House), 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    2.05
  - Building in "Group Facilities Complex"/Newton Square (Aerial View), 1970s (Box 3, Folder 6)
    4.6
  - Dedication Ceremonies Gifts from the Gulf Oil Foundation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    1.07
  - Dedication Ceremonies, Gifts from the Gulf Oil Foundation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    1.06
  - Dedication Ceremonies Gift from the Gulf Oil Foundation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    1.5
  - Grand Opening of North Point Village (Martha Pennino, Jack Herrity, Fran Steinbauer)-September, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    1.04
  - Lake Anne Area/"Roundhouse" Sales Center (Aerial View), 1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    4.7
  - Lake Anne Center Development Mid-Summer (Aerial View), 1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    4.8
  - Wiehle Avenue Bridge Dedication "Martha's Bridge"-September, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    4.9
  - Wiehle Avenue Bridge Dedication "Martha's Bridge"-September, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    4.10
  - Wiehle Avenue Bridge Dedication "Martha's Bridge"-September, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    4.11
- Series 3: Oversize, 1970s
  The has three items in the series which include a t-shirt and framed photographs.
  - "Steinbauer Power" T-Shirt, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Opening Dedication of the Dulles Toll Road (Francis Steinbauer, Governor Robb James Wilding-Director of Wastle. Airports)-Framed Photograph, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 2)
    4.1
  - The Signing of the Wiehle Avenue Bridge Agreement (Francis Steinbauer, Chairmen Jack Herrity and Supervisor Martha Pennino)-Framed Photograph with Pen, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    4.2